Alla Rico

allarico11@gmail.com

Address: 335 Park Avenue • Union Beach, NJ 07735• (848)-218-0759

SUMMARY

Passionate dietitian with 8+ years of experience specializing in functional nutrition with a recent interest in nutrigenomics. Empowering others to heal themselves through personalized nutrition, lifestyle changes and mindfulness. Holistic approach to nutrition that helps treat root causes of imbalance, improve immune function, reduce inflammatory factors, optimize metabolic function and reverse symptoms and disease risk.

EDUCATION

B.S. in Nutritional Sciences, Rutgers, the State University of NJ

New Brunswick, NJ May, 2013

Summa Cum Laude, GPA: 3.9

M.A. in Linguistics and Translation, English and Spanish, Voronezh State University

Voronezh, Russia June, 2005

GPA: 3.69

HONORS/

AWARDS

Graduated Summa Cum Laude from Rutgers, the State University of NJ Recipient of the Phillip Alampi Scholarship for the 2012-2013 years

W. Paul Stillman Scholarship for the 2013-2014 years

Rutgers Dean's list

Member of Kappa Omnicon Nu National Honor Society

RELATED

EXPERIENCE

Aurora Space

Union Beach, NJ

February, 2022 – Present time

Outpatient Dietitian at Private Practice

- Provide one-on-one nutritional assessment and counseling taking a holistic approach to health by incorporating food, sleep, stress, fitness, and toxic environmental factors, in the effort to reduce the risk of chronic diseases and to address the root cause analysis of symptoms;
- Develop customized nutrition plans tailored to individual needs. Utilize knowledge of functional medicine to optimize health outcomes and empower clients to achieve their wellness goals:
- Interpret lab results, uncovering key insights, and translating them into actionable recommendations:

- Utilize motivational interviewing techniques to assist patients to make necessary behavior changes to achieve SMART dietary goals;
- Develop and implement weight loss programs;
- Educate clients about how nutrients influence the genome (Nutrigenomics) using an evidence-based DNA analysis;
- Create engaging content across multiple social platforms to amplify my mission and impact.

DaVita Dialysis Center

Brick, Old Branch and Toms River, NJ

January, 2016 – February, 2022

Renal Dietitian

- Provided 1:1 dietary education and counseling of patients, family members and caretakers;
- Assessed and monitored nutritional status of hemodialysis and peritoneal dialysis patients and complete all required company and CMS charting;
- Functioned as Mineral Bone Disease Manager by analyzing lab values monthly and assisting physicians in managing bone health by adjusting oral or IV Vitamin D analog dose based on patient's lab trends; provided recommendations on appropriate administration of phosphate binders and vitamins;
- Served in leadership role of fluid management by ensuring there is a process for target weight assessment and reassessment to improve care, decrease incidence of fluid overload and reduce fluid related morbidity and mortality;
- Developed individualized Medical Nutrition Therapy and goals for patients based on their lab results, medical, economic, and social situation to minimize their disease progression;
- Participated in rounds, IDT meetings, continuous quality improvement (CQI) activities and other interdisciplinary renal team activities;
- Provided group teaching and supported activities for nurses and patient care technicians;
- Utilized motivational interviewing techniques to assist patients to make necessary behavior changes to achieve SMART dietary goals;
- Developed patient educational materials;
- Trained and precepted new dietitians and nutrition students;
- Provided nutritional care at 2-3 clinics at a time.

HMH Bayshore Medical Center

Holmdel, NJ

March, 2016 – May, 2017

Clinical Dietitian

- Provided Nutrition support -TPN and tube feeding;
- Participated in Interdisciplinary patient rounds in ICU;
- Worked in the following units: ICU, surgical, cardiac, oncology, telemetry, neurological;
- Encouraged patients and caregivers to follow recommended food guidelines for well-balanced diets;
- Calculated nutritional requirements and assessed the adequacy of diet and nutrition support;
- Reviewed charts and assessed the nutritional status of patients;

- Collaborated with interdisciplinary care team to meet the nutritional needs of patients;
- Counseled patients regarding special dietary needs.

Nutrition Solutions, LLC

Jamesburg, NJ

February, 2015 – January, 2016

Outpatient Dietitian

- Conducted 1:1 outpatient nutrition counseling in person and via phone;
- Performed nutrition care process including assessment, diagnosis, intervention, monitoring and evaluation;
 - Utilized motivational nutrition counseling techniques to facilitate positive dietary change;
- Assisted with the creation and revision of educational material related to patient care;
- Utilized clinical software applications to facilitate care;
- Presented nutrition information at seminars and ran support group meetings;
- Co-developed and implemented weight loss programs;
- Conducted nutrition seminars to the community;
- Was responsible for moderating and updating the content on the company's Facebook page.

Clove Lakes Health Care and Rehabilitation Center, Inc.

Staten Island, NY

July, 2014 – November, 2015

Clinical Dietitian

- Performed nutritional assessments of residents and initiated change of nutritional care as needed;
- Participated in comprehensive care planning conferences;
- Documented in the resident medical record as required;
- Completed meal rounds to ensure conformance to prescribed diets, adequate food intake and overall meal tolerance;
- Conducted timely review and documentation of residents' inter-disciplinary comprehensive care plans;
- Formulated and updated discharge plans for continuity of nutritional care;
- Conducted quality improvement projects to determine the root causes of unplanned weight loss in the elderly population.

ADDITIONAL CERTIFICATION

Adult Weight Management

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Fluent in Russian and English, basic Spanish